Pete Welding collection, 1958-1995
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress
- Series 8: Sound recordings
  - Subseries 1: Artists, bands, and interviews
    - Don Ellis interview, January 31, 1967, AFC 2011/053: SR086; RXH 3224; on one side of 1 sound tape reel (acetate; 01:00:15): analog, 3 3/4 ips, half track, mono; 7 in.
      00:02:45 DE mentions going back to New York and working with Lucas Foss in a big band, as well as forming a smaller group to play around Buffalo (New York). This smaller group had two drummers and to basses. Upon returning to L.A. DE wanted to form a big band with a large rhythm section: five drummers and four basses.
      00:04:36 PW asks what brought DE to this "rhythmic investigation." DE gives background on his previous experimentations with rhythms, and then discusses studying Indian music with Harihar Rao and discovering new rhythms.
      00:06:37 DE's "all-consuming passion" to develop himself rhythmically.
      00:07:18 DE's background as a composition grad student at UCLA, and where he first met Harihar Rao.
      00:08:15 DE mentions the rising prominence of the sitar in rock music and jazz, and Ravi Shankar's upcoming visit to the United States. DE states that the rock groups "take the easy way out" by just using the sitar drone sound and not the more complex Indian rhythms.
      00:09:34 PW introduces the subject of semi-tones in Indian music, and different scale systems, suggesting that the difference between Indian and Western music is greater than just rhythms. DE gives a somewhat ambiguous reply, asserting that equal temperament rhythms are abominable, and eventually coming around to the power of intonation in blues music.
      00:11:24 PW restates the subject, asking if "tonal ambiguity" isn't just as "excitement inducing" as the rhythms. PW brings up bottle neck slide playing in blues guitar as an example. DE reasserts that, compared to the Indian scale system, Western music is only just scratching the surface. DE goes on to mention his development of a quarter tone trumpet, and how it enables him to explore different sounds and pitches.
      00:13:55 PW and DE discuss exploring tonality in the "massed sound of the orchestra."
      00:15:56 PW asks when DE reorganized or actually formed his current band, if there are any issues with keeping the band working, and how often they play.
      00:18:00 DE discusses the makeup of the band, that not all of the players are professional musicians, and auditioning his rhythm section. DE gives names and background information about the bass players and drummers in his band.
      00:23:38 PW and DE discuss the public interest in the Indian/Western music crossover via jazz and the Beatles.
      00:26:40 PW mentions The Byrds coining "raga rock" and the Beatles' "Norwegian Wood."
      00:29:08 DE talks about Harihar Rao coming to the States to work with jazz musicians, and whether or not American jazz musicians were interested in Indian music at that time. DE asserts that, like jazz, you have to study Indian music to fully appreciate it.
      00:32:34 DE discusses audience reactions and PW circles back to DE's assertion that the rhythms were the crucial part of the music. PW asks how DE maintains the synthesis of Western and Indian music. This leads into a discussion of the differences between the two types of music and their development.
      00:39:20 DE discusses how he goes about combining Eastern and Western music.
      00:44:27 PW asks how long it took the other musicians to play DE's compositions with ease and proficiency.
      00:46:18 PW asks who else in the band is contributing musical arrangements.
      00:48:25 PW and DE talk about an upcoming release on Liberty Records, recorded live at Monterey, and another recorded at the Pacific Jazz festival.
      00:49:24 PW asks about recordings done for Irving Mills/Mills Music. DE explains that Mills was a financial backer that fell through and tried to stop DE from releasing his own recordings.
      00:53:58 PW asks what jobs are available for a big band these days.
      00:55:43 PW asks about Ellis Music Enterprises.
      00:57:00 PW lays out how DE could reach a more specific audience by advertising in the MENC journal and self-publishing a method book.
      01:00:15 End
    - Dave Evans [David Evans], undated, AFC 2011/053: SR791; RAA 59329; 1 sound tape reel (00:26:34): analog, 15 ips, half track, stereo; 10 in.
      Archivist's note: Dr. David Evans is a musicologist.
      Vendor's digitization note: The program has distortion and hiss.
      Start "John Henry"
      00:04:09 "Working on the Building"
      00:07:30 "Jim Steam Shot Lula"
      00:11:49 "Louisiana Blues"
      00:16:19 "Long Haired Doney"
      00:19:21 "Rollin' and Tumblin'"
      00:25:16 unidentified tune #1
      00:26:34 End
    - Dave Evans [David Evans], undated, AFC 2011/053: SR818; RAA 59355; 1 sound tape reel (00:48:22): analog, 15 ips, four track; 10 in., 1/2 in. wide
      Archivist's note: It sounds like more than one vocalist may be heard on the recording. It is possible that the male speaker before unidentified tune #5 is Pete Welding. The recording date is possibly 1972, but this is unconfirmed by accompanying documentation.
      LC engineer's note: The tape is identified in the documentation as a session tape for the Pete Robinson LP, Dialogues for Piano and Reeds, but actually contains a session for Dave Evans. Some song titles are slated. Same artist and (probably) session as SR825.
      Start snippets from prior tape content
      00:00:11 "Nothing But the Devil"
      00:05:05 unidentified tune #1 [false start]
      00:05:43 unidentified tune #1 [false]
      00:05:53 unidentified tune #1
      00:09:56 unidentified tune #2 [fragment]
      00:10:48 unidentified tune #3
      00:18:10 unidentified tune #4 [fragment]
      00:18:59 unidentified tune #5
      00:22:07 unidentified tune #6
      00:30:01 unidentified tune #7
      00:35:01 unidentified tune #8 [fragment]
      00:37:02 unidentified tune #8 [fragment]
      00:37:53 unidentified tune #8
      00:44:03 unidentified tune #9 [breaks off where end of recording tapes over the previous tape content]
      00:45:22 unidentified tune #10 [different guitar]
      00:46:32 unidentified tune #11 [cut off at the end of the tape]
      00:48:22 End
    - Dave Evans [David Evans], August 31, 1972, September 4, 1972, AFC 2011/053: SR825; RAA 59362; 1 sound tape reel (00:33:33): analog, 15 ips, four track; 10 in., 1/2 in. wide
      Archivist's note: "Maggie Campbell" and "Mellow Peaches" were recorded on September 4, 1972; all other songs were recorded on August 31, 1972. see SR818.
      LC engineer's note: The tape only uses three of the four available tracks. The tape was erased and reused at some point. The box is marked as a 1972 session tape for Pete Robinson and Alan Praskin, but actually contains a session for Dave Evans. Song titles are slated. Tape ends abruptly in midsong.
      Start "John Henry" [take 1; preceded by studio talk and false starts]
      00:04:40 "Working on the Building" [take 1; false start]
      00:04:50 "Working on the Building" [take 2]
      00:08:19 "Jim Steam Shot Lula" [take 1; preceded by a very brief snippet of content covered by the current recording]
      00:08:49 "Jim Steam Shot Lula" [unnumbered take]
      00:13:08 "Louisiana Blues" [take 1]
      00:17:39 "Long Haired Doney" [take 1; preceded by a very brief snippet of content covered by the current recording]
      00:20:50 "Rollin' and Tumblin'" [take 1; preceded by a brief snippet of content covered by the current recording and a false start for the current song]
      00:26:45 "Maggie Campbell" [take 1; possible includes part of the song "Future Blues"]
      00:30:23 "Mellow Peaches" [cut off at the end of the tape]
      00:33:33 End
    - Dave Evans [David Evans] - dubs of recordings made in Bentonia, Mississippi, September 6, 1967, AFC 2011/053: SR576; RXH 5437; 1 sound tape reel (00:31:14): analog; 7 in.
      Collector's original ID number: 108.
      Start "Hard Times" by Jacob Owens, vocal, guitar
      00:02:55 "Catfish Blues" (#2) by Jacob Owens, vocal, guitar
      00:05:53 "Blues in Spanish" by Jacob Owens, vocal, guitar
      00:09:08 "Three O'Clock in the Morning" by Jacob Owens, vocal, guitar
      00:13:18 "See See Rider" by Jacob Owens, vocal, guitar
      00:16:23 "Devil Blues (E major)" by Jacob Owens, vocal, guitar
      00:19:00 "Devil Blues (E minor)" by Jacob Owens, vocal, guitar
      00:22:20 "Cherry Ball Blues" by Jacob Owens, vocal, guitar
      00:25:32 "Pearline" by Jacob Owens, vocal, guitar (with knife)
      00:27:50 "See See Blues" by Jacob Owens, vocal, guitar (with knife)
      00:31:14 End
    - Dave Evans [David Evans] - dubs of Mississippi blues music, September 6, 1967, AFC 2011/053: SR589; RXH 5450; 1 sound tape reel (00:31:42): analog, 7 1/2 ips, full track, stereo; 7 in.
      Collector's original ID number: 109.
      Archivist's note: Dr. David Evans is a musicologist. This tape is a dub of part of his fieldwork. The date 9/6/1967 is written on the tape box spine.
      Start "Mean Mistreater" (Woodrow Adams, vocal, harmonica; Curtis Allen, guitar; Fiddlin' Joe Martin, drums). Recorded in Robinsonville, Mississippi on August 28, 1967.
      00:05:53 "Sitting on Top of the World" (same personnel and date as "Mean Mistreater")
      00:09:36 "Bye and Bye Blues" (Houston Stackhouse, vocal, guitar; Carey Mason, guitar). Recorded in Crystal Springs, Mississippi on September 3, 1967.
      00:12:20 "Mean Black Spider" (same personnel and date as "Bye and Bye Blues")
      00:15:22 "Mercy Blues" (Carey Mason, vocal and slide guitar; Houston Stackhouse, guitar)
      00:18:09 "I Hate to Hear My Good Girl Call My Name" (same personnel as "Mercy Blues")
      00:20:44 "Return Mail" (Houston Stackhouse, vocal and slide guitar; Carey Mason, guitar)
      00:23:56 "Traveling Blues" (Mager Johnson, vocal and guitar; Carey Mason, guitar). Recorded in Crystal Springs, Mississippi on September 3, 1967. Abrupt beginning to the song, with one false start.
      00:26:23 "Doodlesville Blues" (Carey Lee Simmons, vocal and guitar). Recorded in Jackson, Mississippi on September 4, 1967.
      00:28:42 "B. and O. Blues" (Jack Owens, vocal and guitar). Recorded in Bentonia, Mississippi on September 6, 1967.
      00:31:42 End
    - Clare Fischer Orchestra (dubs), undated, AFC 2011/053: SR690; RXH 5567; 1 sound tape reel: analog; 7 in.
    - Gary Foster Quartet (dub) - Chet Baker Quartet, 1953, AFC 2011/053: SR634; RXH 5511; 1 sound tape reel: analog; 7 in.
      The Chet Baker Quartet was recorded live at Carleton Theater, in Los Angeles.
    - Bud Freeman #1, June 30-July 1, 1958, AFC 2011/053: SR365; RXH 4607; 1 sound tape reel (Side 1: 00:42:11): analog, 7 1/2 ips, stereo; 7 in.
      Performances by Bud Freeman, Bob Hammer, and Mousey (Mousie) Alexander.
      Vendor's digitization note: There is a gap in the sound on Side 1, from 00:20:11 to 00:21:07
      Start "California Here I Come"
      00:03:00 "I Can't Give You Anything But Love"
      00:06:20 "'S Wonderful"
      00:09:56 "Who Cares"
      00:13:25 "Chicago"
      00:16:37 "Satin Doll"
      00:20:10 Side 1 ends
      00:21:06 "St. Louis Blues"
      00:24:36 "Limehouse Blues"
      00:27:43 "Newport News Blues"
      00:31:08 "Just One of Those Things"
      00:34:48 "Gone with the Wind"
      00:38:44 "A Viking To My Liking"
      00:42:11 End
    - Bud Freeman #2, February 16-17, 1959, AFC 2011/053: SR366; RXH 4608; 1 sound tape reel (Side 1: 00:27:54): analog, 7 1/2 ips, stereo; 7 in.
      Logger's note: Performances by Bud Freeman, Dick Cary, Jimmy Jones, Leonard Gaskin, and George Wettling. The insert on the original tape box contains the titles of the songs and some notes about each song.
      Start "Birth of the Blues"
      00:03:13 "A Foggy Day"
      00:05:23 "Mimi"
      00:07:30 "I've Got It Bad"
      00:09:59 "I Guess I'll Have To Change My Plan"
      00:13:00 "The Very Thought Of You"
      00:17:41 "They're Playing Our Song"
      00:20:00 "Gentleman's Blues"
      00:23:53 "Try a Little Tenderness"
      00:26:22 "We're Through"
      00:27:54 End
    - Blind Boy Fuller (Fulton Allen) / Barbecue Bob (Robert Hicks), undated, AFC 2011/053: SR639; RXH 5516; 1 sound tape reel: analog; 5 in.
      Recordings dubbed from commercial releases.
    - Eddie Gale, undated, AFC 2011/053: SR624; RXH 5502; 1 sound tape reel (Side 1: 00:14:43, Side 2: 00:00:29): analog, 7 1/2 ips, stereo; 5 in.
      Archivist's note: The Side 2 content is unrelated to the Side 1 recording, and is out of scope for this collection.
    - John Galliher (Side 1); Hobart Smith (Side 2), September 28, 1964, AFC 2011/053: SR357; RXH 4600; 1 sound tape reel (Side 1: 00:30:25, Side 2: 00:07:31): analog, 7 1/2 ips, mono; 7 in.
      Collector's original ID number: 218
      Archivist's note: Live recordings, dubbed from recordings made by Bruce Jackson, and related to recordings in the Bruce Jackson and Diane Christian collection (AFC 2011/009). This tape is probably a compilation Jackson sent to a record company. Musicians include John, Jimmy, and Fred Galligher, Bill DeBusk, and Hobart Smith. Recorded in Saltville, Virginia.
      Start [casual talking and strumming on guitar]
      00:02:40 [instrumental with guitar]
      00:05:10 [instrumental with guitar]
      00:06:29 [instrumental with multiple string instruments]
      00:09:53 [instrumental]
      00:14:04 Lyrics: "As a man goin' round taking names, as a man goin' round taking names lord he took my mother's name and he left my heart in pain/as a man goin' round taking names"
      00:17:09 [instrumental with harmonica]
      00:19:34 [instrumental with fiddle]
      00:21:39 [instrumental with fiddle]
      00:24:08 Lyrics: "In these rolling hills of old Virginia by the place I [love] so [?]/where I spend [?] days of [childhood] in a [cabin] where I love to [play]/I love real [cold] and [tall]/[inaudible lines]/I live my life in sorrow"
      00:27:50 Lyrics: "You may ask where I'm headed, you may ask me where I'm going/Well I'm going to the country across the sea and I know I [?] [?] and I know I [?] [?]/I'm bound by the kingdom of the free"
      00:30:25 End
      Start [instrumental]
      00:02:34 [talking, and guitar and fiddle playing]
      00:04:40 [inaudible singing; guitar, fiddle]
      00:06:06 [instrumental; guitar, fiddle]
      00:07:31 End
    - Erroll Garner / Phineas Newborn, undated, AFC 2011/053: SR577; RXH 5438; 1 sound tape reel (00:19:57): analog; 7 in.
      Logger's note: The titles in the documentation do not match the content of the tape.
      Start Unidentified piano music.
      00:02:39 Unidentified piano music.
      00:05:45 Unidentified piano music.
      00:08:50 Unidentified piano music.
      00:11:46 Unidentified piano music.
      00:14:18 Unidentified piano music.
      00:17:10 Unidentified piano music.
      00:19:57 End
    - Stan Getz, New York, 1980, AFC 2011/053: SR220; RXH 4103; 1 sound tape reel (polyester, 00:29:12): analog, 7 1/2 ips, half track, stereo; 7 in.
      Two instrumental works (and possibly more), featuring Stan Getz; possibly recorded in New York. A man's voice can be heard between works 1 and 2. Collector's original ID number: 59.
      Start unidentified work #1
      00:11:05 unidentified work #2
      00:29:12 End
    - Hovanes Getzoian, undated, AFC 2011/053: SR792; RAA 59330; 1 sound tape reel (00:48:20) (master): analog, 15 ips, half track, stereo; 10 in.
      Archivist's note: This recording may have been made on a reused tape, as the information on the tape box seems to be from two different recording sessions, with different artists.
      Vendor's digitization note: The program has distortion and hiss, and is cut off at the end.
    - Hovanes Getzoian #2, undated, AFC 2011/053: SR221; RXH 4104; 1 sound tape reel (polyester, 00:20:42): analog, 15 ips, half track, stereo; 7 in.
      All songs feature drums, sitar, and male solo voice.
      Start first song
      00:10:00 second song
      00:13:06 third song
      00:20:42 End
    - Frank and Jake Gilmore #1, June 24, 1965, AFC 2011/053: SR293; RXH 4179; 1 sound tape reel (00:29:57): analog, 7 1/2 ips, mono; 7 in.
      Personnel: Frank and Jake, vocals and guitars; Ted Bogan, vocals and bass.
      Vendor's digitization note: The recording speeds up near the end of the tape.
      Start "City Of New Orleans" (J.G., vocal)
      00:04:54 "Gone In The Morning" (J.G., vocal)
      00:09:07 "My Little Woman" (F.G., vocal)
      00:11:54 "Keep It Tight" (J.G., vocal)
      00:14:38 "City of New Orleans (Love Is A Killer Diller)" (F.G., vocal)
      00:18:50 "I Am A Stranger" (J.G., vocal)
      00:22:52 fragment of music
      00:24:37 "Keys To the Highway" (T.B., vocal and guitar, F.G., guitar)
      00:26:15 "Beale Street 49" (T.B., vocal and guitar, F.G., guitar)
      00:29:57 End
    - Glory of Negro Song 1-A, undated, AFC 2011/053: SR593; RXH 5454; 1 sound tape reel (00:16:36): analog, 7 1/2 ips, mono; 7 in.
      Probably dubbed from a commercial recording. Collector's original ID number: 55.
    - Benny Goodman: airshots, 1938-1958, AFC 2011/053: SR631; RXH 5508; 1 sound tape reel: analog; 7 in.
    - Benny Goodman Sextet (unissued recordings, Fall 1976); Bob Wilber Trio (January 24, 1964); Soprano Summit, 1st set, at the Big Horn Jazz Festival (June 1, 1975); Wilber, Sutton jam session (June 1, 1975); Soprano Summit, second set (June 1, 1975), 1964-1976, AFC 2011/053: SR213; RXH 4096; 1 sound tape reel (polyester; Side 1: 01:37:31, Side 2: 01:37:31): analog, 3 3/4 ips, quarter track, stereo; 7 in.
      LC engineer's note: Live recordings; some are dubs that are multiple generations removed from the source recordings. The tape was recorded out of relative phase. This was corrected in the transfer.
      Start 1. An unidentified instrumental jazz song
      00:03:40 2. The next unidentified instrumental jazz song
      00:09:58 3. The next unidentified instrumental jazz song
      00:14:55 4. The next unidentified instrumental jazz song
      00:19:23 5. The next unidentified instrumental jazz song
      00:22:13 6. The next unidentified instrumental jazz song
      00:26:47 7. The next unidentified instrumental jazz song
      00:30:32 8. The next unidentified jazz song begins. At the beginning of the song, a vocalist lets out a few grunts and a soft yell, "O!" He hums, grunts, and yells out throughout the first couple minutes of the song.
      00:33:28 9. The next unidentified instrumental jazz song
      00:37:03 10. The next unidentified instrumental jazz song
      00:39:09 11. The next unidentified instrumental jazz song
      00:43:02 12. The next unidentified instrumental jazz song
      00:45:35 13. The next unidentified instrumental jazz song starts- a piano starts playing lightly in the background while people are still talking.
      00:50:22 14. The next unidentified instrumental jazz song
      00:56:49 15. The next unidentified instrumental song
      01:00:29 16. The next song. There is a vocalist. [It seems like it might be the song, "Somebody Else is Taking My Place," but many of the lyrics are different.]
      01:03:05 17. The next unidentified instrumental jazz song
      01:09:57 18. The next unidentified instrumental song
      01:12:30 19. The next unidentified instrumental song
      01:16:23 20. The next unidentified instrumental song. Background chatting can be heard when the song is over.
      01:18:17 21. The next unidentified instrumental song
      01:22:07 22. The next unidentified instrumental song
      01:25:37 23. The next unidentified instrumental song
      01:28:56 24. The next unidentified instrumental song
      01:35:19 25. The next unidentified instrumental song
      01:37:29 26. One note plays and gets cut off
      01:37:30 End
      Start Announcer tells the audience that the band will go on to tour South Africa, and introduces who is playing which instrument.
      00:00:51 "The Mooche"
      00:07:13 "Oriental Strut"
      00:11:18 The announcer [or a band member] announces that they will now hear from their "lovely" vocalist, Marty Grosz. The audience laughs. Marty [presumably] says, "This is one of the nicest transvestite bands I've ever played with. First couple of weeks were rough because of the garter belt chaff, but we've conquered that problem."
      00:12:03 "How Can You Face Me Now"
      00:15:54 "Japansy"
      00:24:06 The announcer/band member starts talking about the album Soprano Summit and that they will now perform "Stealin' Away" ["Steal Away Blues"].
      00:31:23 The announcer/band member says they would like to perform another song - one that is associated with a singer from Duke Ellington's band, Ivy Anderson. He says, "But we have our own Ivy Anderson - Marty Grosz!" The song is, "Rose of the Rio Grande."
      00:36:41 The announcer/performer does a run-through of who is playing what instrument, while they play music in the background.
      00:37:14 They go from announcing who's who and playing music into their next song, which an instrumental: "C-Jam Blues"
      00:51:18 Some music plays - not a song, just some random notes. People in the audience are chatting.
      00:51:52 The next song is an instrumental work: "I Got Rhythm"
      01:06:37 "Panama"
      01:15:56 Announcer/band member explains that the arrangement they just played [name unintelligible on recording] was something that Bob took from original 1911 sheet music from a John [last name unintelligible] orchestra. He then explains that the next song is a piece called, "I Had It, But It's All Gone Now." Sidney Bechet wrote it in 1923 and Bob [Wilber] and him recorded it together in 1958.
      01:16:56 Instrumental song, "I Had It, But It's All Gone Now."
      01:20:30 The next song is announced: Marty Grosz and George Duvivier play "Swing 39"
      01:26:15 "Milneburg Joys"
      01:27:36 Vocalist starts singing
      01:30:53 Next unidentified and instrumental song starts playing. Unidentified and instrumental. You can hear faint chattering in the background.
      01:37:06 The recording ends and the announcer/performer calls out, "Bob Wilber!"
      01:37:11 End
    - The Gospel Kings of Harmony, #1 ("His Eye is on the Sparrow"), September 26, 1961, AFC 2011/053: SR222; RXH 4105; 1 sound tape reel (polyester, 00:22:48): analog, 7 1/2 ips, half track, mono; 7 in.
      All selections: James Artis, Walter Davis, John Scarbough, William Moore, Clarence West (guitar). Guest artists: Sallie Martin, Mattie Keen, The Arthur Logan Folk Singers. Recorded in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania. Collector's original ID number: 146. See SR222 and SR343.
      Start "Come On In the Prayer Room"
      00:02:53 "What a Friend We Have in Jesus"
      00:05:43 "It's Cool Down Yonder (By the Chilly Jordan"
      00:08:41 "I Promised the Lord That I Would Hold Out (Until He Meets Me in Galilee)"
      00:11:38 "His Eye Is on the Sparrow"
      00:13:37 "Nothing But the Blood of Jesus"
      00:15:46 "God Is Everything to Me"
      00:18:44 "What A Friend We Have in Jesus" (duplicate selection)
      00:21:35 "Sit Down on the Banks of the River" (incomplete)
      00:22:48 End
    - The Gospel Kings of Harmony, September 26, 1961, AFC 2011/053: SR343; RXH 4228; 1 sound tape reel (00:18:43): analog, 7 1/2 ips, mono; 5 in.
      Recorded in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania. The vocalists are identified as James Artis; Walter Davis; John Scarbough; William Moore; and Clarence West. Collector's original ID number: 207. See SR222 and SR493.
      Archivist's note: There have been different singing groups known as the Kings of Harmony.
      Start "Come On In The Prayer Room"
      00:02:53 "What A Friend We Have In Jesus"